# Mario J. Badr

CONTACT Information

The Edward S. Rogers Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering

Room 1107, Sandford Fleming Bldg.

10 King's College Road, Toronto, ON M5S 3G4 Canada

University of Toronto

RESEARCH INTERESTS Many/multi-core architectures, cache coherence, interconnection networks, application modelling, design space exploration.

Industry Experience Qualcomm Research Silicon Valley

Santa Clara, California, USA May, 2015 - August, 2015

Intern (C++, OpenCL, Hexagon, CMake) May, 2015 - August, 2015 Used the Multicore Asynchronous Runtime Environment (MARE) to develop a heterogeneous application with multiple domain-specific kernels. Provided feedback to the MARE team on performance issues and bottlenecks.

Environment Canada Intern (Java, XML) Toronto, Ontario, Canada June, 2009 - August, 2010

Implemented new features and bug fixes for the NinJo workstation, a tool for meteorologists. Notable projects include upgrading the visualization framework for lightning strikes to be faster and use significantly less memory, incorporating storm cell data for Canada, and helping to create a configurable view of weather data for a given storm cell.

AWARDS

# Roberto Padovani Intern Scholarship - \$5,000

2015

Awarded to seven Qualcomm Research interns across the globe for outstanding technical contributions made during their internship.

Thomas Noakes & Queen Elizabeth II Graduate Scholarship - \$15,000

2015

Awarded for excellence in science and technology.

#### TA Teaching Excellence Award - \$200

2015

Awarded to four recipients across the three University of Toronto campuses based on nominations, references, and teaching philosophy.

PEER-REVIEWED
PUBLICATIONS

Joshua San Miguel, **Mario Badr**, and Natalie Enright Jerger. *Load Value Approximation*. In Proceedings of the International Symposium on Microarchitecture (MICRO), to appear, December 2014. (acceptance rate: 19%)

Mario Badr and Natalie Enright Jerger. SynFull: Synthetic Traffic Models Capturing a Full Range of Cache Coherence Behaviour. In Proceedings of the International Symposium on Computer Architecture (ISCA), June 2014. (acceptance rate: 18%)

WORKSHOPS, PRESENTATIONS, AND POSTERS

#### Workshop Paper

Ajaykumar Kannan, **Mario Badr**, Parisa Khadem Hamedani and Natalie Enright Jerger. *Offloading to the GPU: An Objective Approach*. In Proceedings of the International Workshop on Parallelism in Mobile Platforms (PRISM), June 2015.

### Poster

Joshua San Miguel, **Mario Badr**, and Natalie Enright Jerger. *Load Value Approximation*. At the International Symposium on Microarchitecture (MICRO), December 2014.

#### Presentation

Mario Badr and Natalie Enright Jerger. SynFull: Traffic Models Capturing Cache Coherence Behaviour. At the International Symposium on Computer Architecture (ISCA), June 2014.

#### Presentation

Mario Badr and Natalie Enright Jerger. SynFull: Synthetic Traffic Models That Capture Cache Coherent Behaviour. At the University of Toronto ECE Graduate Symposium (Connections), May 2014. Awarded Best Oral Presentation.

#### Presentation

Mario Badr and Natalie Enright Jerger. Realistic Synthetic Traffic At the University of Toronto ECE Graduate Symposium (Connections), May 2012.

# TEACHING EXPERIENCE

# **Engineering Strategies and Practice**

1st Year Undergraduates

Teaching Assistant

Tutorials

Supervised students through the design process for a given project and provided feedback on written design documents, with a focus on stimulating an engineering methodology to design.

## **Computer Fundamentals**

1st Year Undergraduates

Teaching Assistant

Tutorials, Computer Lab

Taught the fundamentals of computer programming in C, including data structures, recursion, and sorting algorithms.

# Communication and Design

2nd Year Undergraduates

Teaching Assistant

Tutorials, Computer Lab

Mentored student groups in the implementation of an application that visualizes and finds routes in a city map. Developed six new tutorials in 2017 to help students with software engineering.

#### Computer Organization

3rd Year Undergraduates

Teaching Assistant

Computer Lab

Supervised and helped students implement a simple von Neumann processor using verilog.

#### Computer Architecture

4th Year Undergraduates & Graduates

Teaching Assistant

Computer Lab

Taught computer architecture concepts, including caches, pipelining, out-of-order cores, and cache coherence.

# UNIVERSITY SERVICE

# Appointed Graduate Representative

2015-2016

Executive Committee of Faculty Council - Faculty of Applied Science & Engineering

#### Graduate Representative

2015-2016

Faculty Council - Faculty of Applied Science & Engineering

President
Electrical and Computer Engineering Graduate Students' Society

2015-2016

#### **Bargaining Support Committee Member**

January - April 2014

Canadian Union of Public Employees

## Department Steward

2013-2014

Canadian Union of Public Employees

# Social Event Coordinator

2012-2013

Electrical and Computer Engineering Graduate Students' Society

# Professional Development

## Teaching in Higher Education

2015

One semester course

Learned more about teaching theories and styles and was observed by peers while teaching a tutorial on Computer Architecture. Also developed a course syllabus for a fictitious course.

# Prospective Professors in Training

2014-2015

Thirteen Seminars, One semester course

Began preparations for becoming a professor in academia, attending several seminars and preparing a preliminary teaching dossier and research statement. Also completed a course on Teaching Engineering in Higher Education.

Mini-MBA 2015

Ten Classes

Gained an understanding of fundamental business concepts and applied what I learned in a group-based case competition.

#### **Oral Presentation Skills**

2014

Five Classes

Examined presentation structure and the use of visual aids. Exchanged feedback with peers and the instructor on individual oral presentations.

# Prewriting Strategies for Developing and Organizing Your Ideas

2014

Four Classes

Learned several new strategies for developing and organizing ideas before (and during) the writing process.

# **NSERC Proposal Workshop**

2014

 $Three\ Classes$ 

Examined features of good and bad proposal writing, and exchanged feedback with peers on our own NSERC proposals.

# **Teaching Fundamentals Certificate**

2012-2013

Six Workshops

Improved my teaching skills with workshops on pedagogy, research, academic integrity, and students in difficulty.

## EDUCATION

### University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada

Ph.D., Computer Engineering, September, 2013 - Present

Dissertation: "Developing Novel Evaluation Methodologies for Assessing Multi-Threaded Applications"

Advisor: Natalie Enright Jerger

# University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada

M.A.Sc, Computer Engineering, January, 2014

Thesis: "Synthetic Traffic Models That Capture Cache Coherent Behaviour"

Advisor: Natalie Enright Jerger

# University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada

B.A.Sc, Electrical Engineering, May, 2011